Sample Finding aid for Interlochen Center for The Arts Records, 1927-2005 851981 BImu Bimu C367 2
Bentley Historical Library
Interlochen Center for The Arts records
1927-2005
1935-1994
Bentley Historical Library
Interlochen Center for the Arts.
851981 BImu Bimu C367 2
86.4 linear feet in 92 boxes
51 Volumes scrapbook
1 oversize folders
30.91 GB online
Parent organization of the Interlochen Arts Academy and the Interlochen Arts Camp (formerly the National Music Camp) founded by Joseph Maddy. Includes administrative records of the Center, the Academy and the Camp and personal papers of Maddy, photographs, sound recordings, and motion pictures.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of this record group came from the National Music Camp/Interlochen Center for the Arts (donor no. 1754 ) beginning in 1942. Periodic additions have been received and are expected. Separate accessions have been received from the C. M. Tremaine family (donor no. 5550 ) and others (donor nos. 6669, and 7769 ).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research. Digitized audio files are currently available only in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Maddy, Interlochen's founder and long-time leader, was born in Wellington, Kansas, on October 21, 1891. Both his parents were educators. His father taught before becoming a banker, and his mother served as county school superintendent. Both also enjoyed performing music, especially his mother, an accomplished amateur musician. Their first son, Harry, a year and a half older, served as a role model in Joe's early musical career.
As youths, the two brothers joined the newly formed Wellington Boys Band. Its director took the group on a musical camping trip, which Joe greatly enjoyed. Later, the boys graduated to the town band. They also performed in the family quartet, which was expanded during their early teens when another talented musical family, the Petits, moved to town. The Petits' youngest daughter, Fay, who years later eventually became Mrs. Joseph Maddy, and the two families spent part of a summer playing music while camping together.
On becoming president, Odell spent much of his first year meeting with Interlochen supporters both on campus and throughout the country in order to define the institution's future goals. Then, he announced a major fund-raising program to renovate facilities and increase endowment, adding that he hoped to make Interochen better known both in its home area and beyond. In fact, during Odell's tenure, the camp was named one of the top ten camps in the country and the World Youth Symphony Orchestra performed in the Cultural Olympiad at the 1996 Olympics in Atlanta, GA.
Odell was succeeded by Edward J. Downing. During Downing's time in office, Interlochen merged with The Pathfinder School, a local independent day school for pre-school through eighth-grade students. Downing retired in 2002 and was succeeded by Jeffery S. Kimpton in 2003.
Arrangement
Summary Contents List
Chronological, mainly 1920-1966 (boxes 1-15)
Joseph Maddy (box 1)
Camp History (boxes 1-2)
Histories and anniversaries
Orchestra Camp Colony
Other Music camps
National High School Orchestra
National Music Camp
Pennington family
Camp records, 1935-1945 (boxes 3-12)
Camp records, 1945-1966 (boxes 12-13)
Special correspondence, mainly 1928-1966 (boxes 13-15)
Subject, (boxes 15-46 and 87-91)
mainly 1928-1989 (boxes 15-46)
Joseph Maddy (boxes 15-25)
Appearances
Broadcasting
Civic Music
Music education
Publications, speeches, and writings
University of Michigan
Giddings and Tremaine (boxes 25-26)
Interlochen (Camp and Academy) (boxes 26-41)
Alumni
Broadcasting
Campus
Financial
Fund raising
Interlochen Arts Festival
Interlochen Press
International
International Society of Music Educators
Michigan, State of
Organizations
Petrillo Controversy
Publicity/Promotion
Special Events
Traverse City
U.S. Government
University of Michigan
Camp (boxes 41-44)
Academy (boxes 44-46)
College (box 46)
1930-2003, Later Acquisition (boxes 87-91)
Alumni-Grainger, Percy (box 87)
Henethorne, Margaret-Federation of Music Clubs, WI (box 88)
Federation of Music Clubs, 1959-News Releases, Chron. (box 89)
News Releases, Alpha-Special Events, Jacobi Dinner (box 90)
Special Events, Milliken Dinner-Strategic Planning Update (box 91)
Post-Maddy Administrators; 1958-recent (boxes 46-56, 66 and 85-86)
Donald Gillis (boxes 46-47)
John Merrill (box 47)
Margaret Stace (box 47)
George Wilson (boxes 47-48)
Karl Haas (boxes 48-49)
Roger Jacobi (boxes 50-56)
Boal (boxes 66-67 and 85-86)
Szady (box 67)
Odell (box 86 and 67)
Downing (box 86)
Boards, 1928-1989 (boxes 56-64)
Board of Advisors (box 56)
Board of Control (box 57)
Board of Trustees (boxes 57-64)
Previously Closed Files (box 65)
Recent Leaders, 1989-1995 (boxes 66-66)
Printed, mainly 1928-1989 (boxes 68-72 and 81-83)
Scrapbooks, 1928-1979 (with gaps)
Visual Materials (boxes 73-79)
Sound Recordings (boxes 79-80 and 84)
Scope and Contents
The records of the Interlochen Center for the Arts were received in installments over many years. They came from several sources: the Camp office in Ann Arbor, the Tremaine family, an alumni leader, and various administrators at Interlochen, but the greatest proportion was assembled from Maddy's home and Interlochen offices, after his death, by Margaret (Peg) Stace, his long-time assistant.
The Camp files for 1935-1945 comprise the major portion received in their original order, and they were in disarray because of frequent changes in Camp secretaries and the practice of moving the office (along with relevant files) from Ann Arbor to Interlochen and back each summer. Also, Maddy kept many items of a personal and confidential nature at home.
In processing the records, an attempt was made both to preserve the original order, where ascertainable, and to highlight major subjects and individuals, some of whose importance only became apparent with the passage of time. A separate name index is available for major correspondents. Where extant, explanatory historical and background information has been placed at the front of records categories. Because of Maddy's influence on the development of Interlochen both past and present, his correspondence with later administrators has been included if practical, under "Administration" in their papers.
The surviving records have been divided into nine series: Chronological, Subject, Post-Maddy Administrators, Boards, Closed, Printed, Visual Materials, Sound Recordings, and Scrapbooks. The Chronological focuses on Maddy and the Camp until 1966 while the Subject, is composed of two subseries. The first, mainly 1928-1989, though also heavily relating to Maddy, also includes much on developments through the '90s. The second subseries, 1930-2003, Later Acquisition represents a group of files that were acquired in 2005. Many files pertain to the early camp and Joesph Maddy. The Post-Maddy Administrators series begins in the late 1950's when Maddy expanded the staff in anticipation of making Interlochen a year-round institution and continues unto the most recent accession. Boards (governing bodies) starts with the Camp's founding in 1928 and ends in 1989 while the Closed series covers the Maddy, Haas, and Wilson administrations through 1971. Printed offers coverage to the present but is more complete for the early years through the 1980's. While the Visual Materials and Sound Recordings series extend from the 1920's into the 1980's, it offers best coverage from 1924 to 1942 Scrapbooks, with gaps in the early years, documents both Maddy and the Camp, beginning with the National High School Orchestra and ending with the Camp's 50th anniversary celebration in 1978.
Interlochen (Mich.); Music -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Musicians -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Radio and music -- Michigan.; Radio broadcasting -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Music camps -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Interlochen (Mich.); Music -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Music camps -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Musicians -- Michigan -- Interlochen.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Slides.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; American Federation of Musicians.; Interlochen Arts Academy (Interlochen, Mich.); Interlochen Arts Camp.; Interlochen Center for the Arts.; National Music Camp.; Petrillo, James C. (James Caesar), 1892-1984; Maddy, Joseph E. (Joseph Edgar), 1891-1966; National Music Camp.; Interlochen Center for the Arts.; National Music Camp.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973; Charters, W. W. (Werrett Wallace), 1875-1952; Dow, Alden B., 1904-1983; Dow, Herbert Henry, 1866-1930; Dunham, Franklin, 1892-; Dykema, Peter W. (Peter William), 1873-1951; Earhart, Will.; Fennell, Frederick.; Gordon, Edgar B.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961; Grofe, Ferde, 1892-1972; Hanson, Howard, 1896-1981; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987; Insull, Samuel, 1859-1938; Kresge, Stanley Sebastian, 1900-; Maazel, Lorin, 1930-2014; Maddy, Joseph E. (Joseph Edgar), 1891-1966; Ormandy, Eugene, 1899-1985; Sibelius, Jean, 1865-1957; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951; Waller, Judith C. (Judith Cary), 1889-1973; Whiteman, Paul, 1890-1967; Maddy, Joseph E. (Joseph Edgar), 1891-1966; Johnson, Thor.; Wilson, George.
- Chronological, 1920-1966
  Scope and Contents
  The Chronological series emphasizes Maddy and the Camp until 1966. It is divided into several subseries: Maddy biography, Camp history, Camp files, 1935-1945, Camp files, 1945-1966, and Special correspondence. The first two subseries provide documentation for the earliest years. The series is supplemented by the Subject series which is especially useful for Camp operations and the founding of the Academy.
  - Subject Files, 1928-1989
    The Subject Files series, is divided into two subseries. The first, mainly 1928-1989, emphasizes Maddy and his administration of Interlochen although later materials, especially for the decade or two following his death, are also included. It has six sub-subseries: Joseph Maddy, Giddings and Tremaine, Interlochen, Camp, Academy, and College. The Maddy sub-subseries focuses on his career activities apart from Interlochen while Giddings and Tremaine contains background information and publications of the two other early Camp leaders. Interlochen covers subjects affecting the institution in general, mainly the Camp before 1962 and both it and the Academy thereafter. The remaining sub-subseries focus on detailed planning and operation of: the National Music Camp, Interlochen Arts Academy, and proposed Interlochen College of Creative Arts.
    - Card index (Box 92)
    - Maddy
      The Maddy sub-subseries contains information on his professional activities outside Interlochen. Many of them relate to his role as a faculty member of the university. Although direct ties to Interlochen are lacking, virtually everything he did somehow involved the institution he founded. The sub-subseries consists of six subsections: Appearances, Broadcasting, Civic Music, Music Education, Publications, Speeches and Writings, and University of Michigan.
      - Broadcasting
        "Broadcasting", mainly 1931-1948, documents Maddy's non-Interlochen radio work. It includes his correspondence and scripts for instrumental and vocal education programs as well as correspondence, reports, and other records on his attempt to create an alternative to commercial radio, largely using the new FM technology. Scripts include those used by announcers Mike Wallace and Ward Quaal and texts of radio addresses on Americanism by Murray Van Wagoner, Leo Fitzpatrick, and Karl Detzer. Researchers will also want to check "Civic Music" for Maddy's wartime broadcasts and "Music Education" for the professional educators' program "Music and American Youth." Since much of his non-Interlochen broadcasting was done for the university, reports and other information about it can be found under "University of Michigan" (6) in this sub-subseries. Recordings and a movie film of his instructional programs can be found in the Visual Materials and Sound Recordings series.
        - University of Michigan radio, 1931-1954
          - History (Box 16)
            Online Streaming in Media Collections Online
            https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/pv63gh62z
          - General
            - Papers, 1931-1954; 8 folders (Box 16)
            - U. of M. student papers, circa, 1935-1936 (Box 16)
            - Summer survey responses, 1937 (Box 16)
            - W.P.A.-student workers, 1938-1940 (Box 16)
          - Program materials
            - Band & gen'l instrument lessons
              - February and March, including course book, 1931 (Box 16)
              - February and March, 1932
                - Announcements and scripts (Box 16)
                - Survey of participating schools (Box 16)
                - Correspondence (Box 16)
              - October-December-course book, 1932 (Box 16)
              - 1933-1935-scripts and lesson plans, 2 folders (Box 16)
              - 1935-1936
                General
                WJR and WMAQ
                - Correspondence
                - Production (mainly NBC) (Box 16)
                - General, 2 folders (Box 16)
                - Listener (Box 16)
                - General (Box 16)
                - Instruction book orders (Box 16)
                - Participating schools, circa, 1936 (Box 16)
                - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 16)
                - Network plans for "Musical Youth" (Box 16)